Guide to the Wolfgang F. Stolper Papers, 1892-2001 (bulk [1930s-1990s]
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wolfgang F. Stolper papers 1892-2001 (bulk [1930s-1990s])
Stolper, Wolfgang F.
29 linear feet Extent: 18,525 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Professor emeritus of economics, University of Michigan. Stolper died in 2002. The papers of Wolfgang F. Stolper (ca. 9900 items) span the period from 1947-1988, with the bulk of the materials dated between 1960 and the mid 1970s. Most of the collection is comprised of Professor Stolper's files and notes from his work in Nigeria, Tunisia, and other missions to Africa. These work files document his career as a practitioner--literally working "in the field"--of development economics.
RL.01258
Language: English, German, and French.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, some of the materials in the additions to this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Wolfgang F. Stolper were donated to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1993, 1995, and 2002.
Biographical Note
1912 Born in Vienna, Austria on May 13
1930-34 Attended the Universities of Berlin, Bonn, and Zurich
1935 M.A., Economics, Harvard University
1936-41 Instructor and Tutor, Economics, Harvard University
1938 Ph.D., Economics, Harvard University
1941 Publication (with Paul A. Samuelson):
Protection and Real Wages, Review of Economic Studies, November 9, 1941
1941-49 Assistant Professor (1941-48), Associate Professor (1948-49), Swarthmore College
1947-48 Guggenheim Foundation Fellowship, University of Zurich
1949-date Associate Professor (1949-53), Professor (1953-82), Director of Center for Research on Economic Development (1963-70), Professor Emeritus (1982 - ), University of Michigan
1960 Publication:
Germany Between East and West (National Planning Association),
and
The Structure of the East German Economy (Harvard University Press)
1961-1962 Head, Economic Planning Unit,; Federal Ministry of Economic Development, in Lagos, Nigeria
1963-1964, 1964-1965 Chief, USAID economic mission to Tunisia
1966 Publication:
Planning Without Facts: Lessons in Resource Allocation from Nigeria's Development (Harvard University Press)
1966 Fulbright Professor, University of Heidelberg
1967 Member, Economic Section, International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD)
1967 Head, IBRD Mission to Togo and Dahomey
Dahomey is now called Benin (name changed in 1975).
1970 Member, USAID Mission to Nigeria
1981 Member, UN Mission to Malawi
1983 Chief, IBRD Mission to Benin
1994 Publication of
Joseph Alois Schumpeter: The Public Life of a Private Man (Princeton University Press)
In addition to the places listed above, Professor Stolper participated in economic missions to Malta (1963), Liberia (1963), and Turkey (1968), and worked as a consultant to the Ford Foundation, USAID, the United Nations, and the IBRD (the World Bank). He also held various visiting professorships/lecturing posts at the Universities of Zurich, Heidelberg, and Munster.
His professional affiliations include membership in the American Economic Association, the Nigerian Economic Association, the International Instititute of Public Finance, and the International Schumpeter Society (founding president).
Collection Overview
The papers of Wolfgang F. Stolper span the period from 1947-1988, with the bulk of the material dated between 1960 and the mid 1970s. Most of the collection is comprised of Professor Stolper's files and notes from his work in Nigeria, Tunisia, and other missions to Africa. These work files document his career as a practitioner--literally working in the field--of development economics. The papers are organized into eight series: Nigeria; Tunisia; Other Missions; Writings; Speeches, Lectures, and Conferences; Schumpeter; University of Michigan and Teaching Material; and General Correspondence. The Nigeria Series, the first and largest, contains his work files from his job as head of the Economic Planning Unit (EPU) in the Federal Ministry of Economic Development in Lagos, Nigeria from 1961-62(sent there under the auspices of the Ford Foundation). As head of the EPU, Stolper co-authored the first ever National Development Plan, 1962-68for the Federation of Nigeria. As such, his papers present an extensive and thorough picture of the Nigerian economy at that time. Once top secret files, they include detailed statistical data on each industry, industrialization plans, reports on marketing board policies, maps, and demographics data. Of great interest to researchers on the Nigerian economy might be Stolper's personal diary, a 393-page typewritten account of his two years in Nigeria. The next two series pertain to his work in Tunisia (1972),and other economic missions to Africa including Dahomey (now Benin) and Togo (1967), Benin (1983)and Malawi (1981).He was sent to these countries under the auspices of USAID, the UN and the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD, also known as the World Bank). The files from these three series alone make up eight of the fourteen storage boxes that house the entire collection. Also in the collection are some notes, papers and drafts of Professor Stolper's work pertaining to Joseph Schumpeter. The collection as a whole is restricted, so that persons interested in viewing the papers during Professor Stolper's lifetime must first obtain his permission.
Stolper's name is perhaps most recognizable for the theoretical piece written with Paul A. Samuelson on what has come to be known as the Stolper-Samuelson Theorem (see Protection and Real Wages, Review of Economic Studies, Nov. 1941). This theorem, one of the core results of the Hecksher-Ohlin model of international trade, essentially states that an increase in the relative domestic price of a good (for example, via the imposition of a tariff) unambiguously raises the real return to the factor of production used intensively in producing that good (and lowers the real return to the other factor). This paper analyzed precisely for the first time the effect of trade or protection on real wages. At present, there is nothing (aside from reprints of the article) in this collection of papers dealing with the Stolper-Samuelson Theorem.
The fourth series, Writings, contains notes, drafts, manuscripts and reprints of any articles found in the collection but excluding those related to Joseph Schumpeter. Some highlights include drafts of Investments in Africa South of the Sahara, notes and drafts of his book Planning Without Facts: Lessons in Resource Allocation from Nigeria's Development, and articles on smuggling in Africa.
The fifth series, Speeches, Lectures and Conferences, contains material (excluding those pertaining to Schumpeter) from public speaking engagements and conferences attended by Professor Stolper. One item that might be of interest is a speech recorded on magnetic tape titled Problems of our Foreign Aid Program that dates from around the 1950's.
Another of Professor Stolper's research interests is the history of economic thought, and this collection's Schumpeter Series contains some notes, papers and drafts of Professor Stolper's work pertaining to Joseph Alois Schumpeter. Stolper was afforded a unique and personal relationship with Schumpeter, studying under him first at the University of Bonn and then at Harvard, and also through Schumpeter's position as a close friend of Gustav and Toni Stolper (Wolfgang's father and stepmother, respectively). Included in this series is a book (in German) that Professor Stolper co-wrote with Horst Claus Recktenwald and Frederic M. Scherer titled Uber Schumpeters »Theorie der wirtschaftlichen Entwicklung«, 1988.
The addition (02-0207) (8625 items, 14 linear feet; dated 1892-2001) contains correspondence with colleagues, including Paul Samuelson, Gottfried Haberler, and other prominent economists; class lectures (1930s); as well as writings about J. A. Schumpeter, economic development, and other topics. Also writings, reports, diaries, and other documents (mainly 1960s) about the economies of Nigeria, Tunisia, Liberia, Togo, and the Ivory Coast. In addition, there are 12 black-and-white and 18 color photographs; one x-ray; and 16 electronic documents on 3 floppy disks. This addition is unprocessed.
Processing Note
A side note on the processing of this collection is that the folders were labeled with Professor Stolper's original titles, and items were very rarely moved to different folders. Consequently, rather than consolidating all the pieces of correspondence into one folder, they were left dispersed throughout the collection in the same files they came in. Some of the papers are written in German and French, but the bulk is in English.
Subject Headings
Stolper, Wolfgang F.; Samuelson, Paul Anthony, 1915-; Haberler, Gottfried, 1900-; World Bank -- Africa; Nigeria. Federal Ministry of Economic Development; University of Michigan. Dept. of Economics; Economists -- United States; Economics -- History; Economics -- Study and teaching (Higher); Economics -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor; Finance, Public -- Nigeria; Economic development; Developing countries -- Economic conditions; Nigeria -- Economic policy; Benin -- Economic policy; Togo -- Economic policy; Malawi -- Economic policy; Tunisia -- Economic policy; Côte d'Ivoire -- Economic policy; Liberia -- Economic policy; Nigeria -- Economic conditions -- 1960-; Africa -- Economic conditions -- 1960-; Diaries; Color photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Machine-readable records
Contents of Collection
- Nigeria Series, 1961-62
  Comprised of Professor Stolper's work files from his job as head of the Economic Planning Unit for the Federal Ministry of Economic Development in Lagos. Sent there under the auspices of the Ford Foundation, one of Professor Stolper's accomplishments was to help coordinate and write the first-ever National Development Plan for Nigeria. The files, after the diary, are arranged in alphabetical order. Highlights include Dr. Stolper's personal diary; drafts of an article titled The Development of Nigeria commissioned and published by Scientific American; detailed information and data on all aspects of the Nigerian economy; and various letters which are dispersed throughout the series.
  - Diary, 1961-62 (Box 1)
  - Agricultural Development Plans in East Nigeria (Box 1)
  - American Mission (May - June 1961visit) (Box 1)
  - Capital -- Regional Breakdown (Box 1)
  - Council of Ministers paper (Box 1)
  - Development Corporation (Box 1)
  - Education (Box 1)
  - Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) Mission (Box 1)
  - Federal Grants to the Regions (Box 1)
  - Financial Resources (Federal) (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation Correspondence (Box 1)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT): Coffee, Tea, Cocoa, etc. (Box 1)
  - Ibadan/Chicago conference, etc. (Box 1)
  - International Labor Organization (I.L.O.) National Provident Fund (Box 1)
  - International Monetary Fund (IMF) Background Material (Box 1)
  - Incentive Legislation etc. (Box 1)
  - Industrialization (Box 1)
  - Institute of Commonwealth Studies (Box 1)
  - Interviews (Box 1)
  - Joint Planning Committee (JPC) papers (Box 1)
  - Land Settlement and Farm Institutes (Box 1)
  - Lefeber, Louis (Box 1)
  - Lewis Report (Box 1)
  - Manpower Planning Eastern Region (Box 2)
  - Manuwa Report (Box 2)
  - Maps: Misc. (Box 2)
  - Marketing Board Accounts: Western Region (Box 2)
  - Marketing Board: Northern Region (Box 2)
  - Marketing Board Reports (Box 2)
  - Ministry Programs (Box 2)
  - Misc. Economic Planning Unit (EPU) Memoranda (Box 2)
  - Misc. Statistics and Papers Northern Nigeria (Box 2)
  - National Economic Council (NEC): Memoranda and Comments (Box 2)
  - National Economic Council: JPC Memoranda and Comments (Box 2)
  - National Plan, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - National Plan: Appendices (Box 2)
  - National Plan: Chapters 1 - 10 (Box 2)
  - National Plan: Draft (Box 2)
  - National Plan: October Revision, Northern Nigeria (Box 2)
  - National Plan Original (Box 2)
  - Original of First National Plan, Stage A (Box 2)
  - National Plan: Preliminary Versions (Box 3)
  - National Plan: Resources (Box 3)
  - National Plan, Stage Intermediate A (Box 3)
  - NEC and JPC Reports (Box 3)
  - NEC documents (Box 3)
  - NEC papers: II (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings on the Plan (Box 3)
  - Niger dams (Box 3)
  - Nigeria: First Visit (Box 3)
  - Nigeria: General (Box 3)
  - Nigerian Institute of Social and Economic Research: Info. Bulletin (Box 3)
  - Oils and Fats (Box 3)
  - Past Capital Programs (Box 4)
  - Petroleum (Box 4)
  - Plan Annexures (Box 4)
  - Press Clippings: Misc. (Box 4)
  - Production Estimates Nigeria (Box 4)
  - Resource Mobilization (Box 4)
  - Revenue Projections: Eastern Region (Box 4)
  - Revenue Projections: Northern Region (Box 4)
  - Revenue Projections: Western Region (Box 4)
  - Rivkin Testimony (Box 4)
  - Scientific American (Box 4)
  - Standing Committee on Statistics: Census, Balance of Payments, Gov. Accounts (Box 4)
  - Standing Committee on Statistics: Econ Report, Stock Exchange, Labor Statistics, Price Data (Box 4)
  - Standing Committee on Statistics: Marketing Board (Box 4)
  - Standing Committee on Statistics: Minutes and Agenda (Box 4)
  - Standing Committee on Statistics: Papers (Box 5)
  - Sterling Assets: Northern Region (Box 5)
  - Telecommunication Program (Box 5)
  - Timber (Box 5)
  - Tin (Box 5)
  - Transport Coordination (Box 5)
  - Vasey, Sir Ernest (Box 5)
  - Wels, Jerome: paper (Box 5)
  - Western Housing Corporation (Box 5)
  - Western Nigeria Development Plan (Box 5)
  - Western Region Misc. Documents (Box 5)
  - Work Sheets Expenditures Programs (Box 5)
  - World Bank Material and First Draft Development Material: Eastern Region (Box 5)
  - World Bank Mission: July -Aug 1961 (Box 5)
- Tunisia Series, 1963-65, 1970s (Box 5)
  The bulk of this series is made up of work files from Professor Stolper's 1963-65 economic mission in Tunis, but it also contains material (notes, data, and drafts) for a paper he co-wrote with Jacob G. Kleve in 1973 titled Investments, Employment and Productivity in the Tunisian Economy, 1961-1971, and a book titled
  Investments, Employment and Output Per Man in the Tunisian Economy, 1961-1971 (University of Michigan Center for Research on Economic Development)
  written in 1974. The files are arranged in alphabetical order; the book is located at the end of the series.
  - AMS (Box 6)
  - Checking (Box 6)
  - Chemicals Final Tables (Box 6)
  - Chemicals Final Tables: Text (Box 6)
  - Chemicals Recalculation Fertilizer: Other Subsectors (Box 6)
  - CPB CAT (Box 6)
  - Draft from Notebook (Box 6)
  - Energy Draft (Box 6)
  - Etude Sur l'Analyse des Ecarts entre les Previsions et les Realisations du Budget Economique 1965-68 (Box 6)
  - Government of Tunisia Report (Box 6)
  - I.A.A. (Box 6)
  - IBRD Correspondence (Box 6)
  - IBRD Report: Current Economic Position and Prospects (Box 6)
  - Economic Development of Tunisia (Box 6)
  - IBRD International Development Association (Box 6)
  - IME (Industries Mecaniques et Electriques) Final Text and Annex (Box 6)
  - Industry Breakdown (Box 6)
  - Investissements, Emploi et Productivite dans L'economie Tunesienne, 1961-1971, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Investments (Box 6)
  - Kleve, J.G.: Various Papers (Box 7)
  - Kleve, M. International Comparison Project (Box 7)
  - Le Budget de Fonctionnement (Titre I) (Box 7)
  - Le Financement des Investissment en Tunisie, 1961-1971 (Box 7)
  - L'industrie diverses (Box 7)
  - MCCV (Materiaux Construction Ceramique Verre) Final (Box 7)
  - Metal Working (Box 7)
  - Investments and Employment and Productivity in the Tunisian Economy, 1961-1971, (folders 1 and 2 out of three) (Box 7)
  - Investments and Employment and Productivity in the Tunisian Economy, 1961-1971, (folder 3) (Box 7)
  - Ministre du Plan: Notes Concernnant Le Projet Emploi (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Material, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Notes Sur L'emploi (Box 7)
  - NUP SIAPE (Box 7)
  - P.J.B. 68-76 (Box 7)
  - Secteur Chimie (Box 7)
  - Note sur l'evolution des Revenus (Box 7)
  - Steel Mill (Box 7)
  - Technical Notes (Box 7)
  - Transport and Communications Sectors (Box 7)
  - Tunisia, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Tunisia: Draft (Box 7)
  - Tunisia Tables (Box 7)
  - Unlabeled Folder (Box 7)
  - Unlabeled Folder (Box 7)
  - Investments, Employment and Output per Man in the Tunisian Economy, 1961-1971, published by the University of Michigan Center for Research on Economic Development, Sept. 1974 (Box 8)
- Other Missions Series, 1967-83 (Box 8)
  Comprised of files from economic missions to Togo and Dahomey (1967), Nigeria (1970), Malawi (1981),and Benin (1983). Included are correspondence with the missions' sponsoring organizations, memoranda, and background reading (economic briefing reports, maps, etc.) on each country. The files are arranged chronologically.
  Dahomey is now called Benin (name changed in 1975).
  - Togo and Dahomey (1967)Memoranda, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - USAID Mission to Nigeria (1970) (Box 8)
  - Nigeria Review Team (1970)Draft Final Report, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Malawi mission (May-June 1981) (Box 8)
  - Benin Mission (1983), (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Planning and the Plan in Benin: Mission Report (1983) (Box 8)
- Writings Series (Articles, Drafts and Notes), 1947-1988 (Box 8)
  Includes notes, drafts, manuscripts, and reprints of articles, excluding those pertaining to Joseph A. Schumpeter. The files cover the period from 1947 to 1988, and are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - American Balance of Payments (ca. late 1950s) (Box 9)
  - Appendix Tables which were redone (ca. late 1950s) (Box 9)
  - Bhagwati: Readings in International Trade (1969) (Box 9)
  - Budget Probleme des Zaire (1975) (Box 9)
  - Bulletin: Presse und Informationsant der Bundesregierung (1972), (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Common Market Input-Output Tables (ca. 1959-65) (Box 9)
  - Construction Tables, Transport and Communications Tables (ca. late 1950s) (Box 9)
  - European Economic Problems (1947) (Box 9)
  - Exchange Controls and Parallel Market Economics (ca. 1985) (Box 9)
  - Germany (West): Production (ca. 1960) (Box 9)
  - International Food Organization (IFO) Research (1980) (Box 9)
  - International Monetary Fund (IMF) and World Bank (IBRD) Reports (1972-74) (Box 9)
  - Industrial Court Cause 77/66: Memorandum to the Kenyan Oil Industry (Box 9)
  - Industrial Production of Soviet Germany (1956), (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - International Trade Text, MS Revision (ca. late 1950's) (Box 9)
  - Investments in Africa South of the Sahara, Part II (1959), (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Investments in Africa South of the Sahara: Tables (1959) (Box 10)
  - Investments in Africa South of the Sahara: Text (1959) (Box 10)
  - Leff, Nathaniel: paper (1986) (Box 10)
  - Mailing Lists (ca. late 1950s) (Box 10)
  - Misc. Articles on Africa (ca. late 1950's) (Box 10)
  - Misc. Articles, Notes and Clippings (late 1980's) (Box 10)
  - Misc. Loose Items (late 1950's - 1970's) (Box 10)
  - National Accounting in East Germany (1959) (Box 10)
  - New Palgrave: August Losch entry (1985) (Box 10)
  - Planning Without Facts, Chapters I - IV (1964) (Box 10)
  - Planning Without Facts, Chapters V - VII (1964) (Box 10)
  - Planning Without Facts, Chapters I - VII (1964) (Box 10)
  - R-General (contains copy of "National Accounting in E. Germany" ), 1959 (Box 10)
  - Reconstruction and Development in Nigeria (1971) (Box 10)
  - Smuggling Subseries (Box 11)
    - Effects of Smuggling Under African Conditions (ca. early 1980s) (Box 11)
    - Smuggling Study, Early Version (before co-authorship with Alan Deardorff), 1980s (Box 11)
    - Smuggling - Draft (1985) (Box 11)
    - Smuggling and Unrestricted Trade -Berg Manuscript (1985) (Box 11)
    - Smuggling in Africa: Berg Study, etc. (1985) (Box 11)
    - Effects of Smuggling Under West African Conditions (1988) (Box 11)
  - Stock Exchange (late 1950's) (Box 11)
  - Unlabeled Notebook (ca. mid 1980s), (2 folders) (Box 11)
- Speeches, Lectures and Conferences Series, late 1950s - 1969 (Box 11)
  Documents Professor Stolper's public speaking engagements and activities at conferences, excluding those pertaining to Joseph Schumpter. The files are arranged in chronological order.
  - Speech on magnetic tape: "Problems of Our Foreign Aid Program" (ca. 1950's?) (Box 12)
  - Prospects for East German Economic Expansion (1959) (Box 12)
  - National Council of Churches Conference (Nov. 8-11, 1962) (Box 12)
  - Economic Development Institute (1964) (Box 12)
  - Luxembourg Lectures (Sept. 1965) (Box 12)
  - Luxembourg Lectures: Five Lectures on the Movement of Goods and the Equalization of Factor Prices (1965) (Box 12)
  - Luxembourg Lectures (1965) (Box 12)
  - Agricultural Development Council Conference (Nov 1965) (Box 12)
  - Economic Development Institute (March 1966) (Box 12)
  - Talk given at First Presbyterian Church, East Aurora, NY (Dec. 12, 1967) (Box 12)
  - Budget as an Allocation Device and Economic Growth (March 29, 1968), (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Glasgow Conference Summary (1969) (Box 12)
- Schumpeter Series, 1966-1988 (Box 12)
  Contains Professor Stolper's drafts, manuscripts, and notes for articles and books pertaining to the eminent Austrian economist, Joseph Schumpeter. The files are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Fiscal and Monetary Policy in the Context of Development: A Schumpeterian Approach (1981) (Box 13)
  - Joseph Alois Schumpeter (ca. 1966) (Box 13)
  - Manuskript: Schumpeter (1983) (Box 13)
  - Paris Paper -- J.A. Schumpeter: the Role of Government (Sept. 1983), (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Schumpeter and the German and Austrian Socialization Attempts of 1918-1919 (1985) (Box 13)
  - Schumpeter Policy Long Draft: Correspondence Relating to Son (1984) (Box 13)
  - Schumpeter -- The Political Economist for the Nineties? (1986), (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Schumpeter -- Stolper book draft (ca. 1983) (Box 13)
  - Schumpeter's Theorie der Wirtschaftlichen Entwicklung, 1988 (Box 13)
  - Stopler-Seidl Drafts (ca. 1985), (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Uber Schumpeters Theorie der Wirtschaftlichen Entwicklung (published 1988) (Box 13)
- University of Michigan and Teaching Material Series, 1959-1975 (Box 13)
  The file titled "Course Outlines on Economic Development" contains different syllabi and reading lists compiled by a friend of Professor Stolper's. The "Doctoral Committees" file contains paperwork pertaining to Ph.D. committees that he sat on at the University of Michigan. Finally, the "Workload Records" folder contains paperwork listing the classes that Professor Stolper taught each semester at Michigan. Files are arranged in chronological order.
  - Course Outlines on Economic Development (1959) (Box 14)
  - ECO 141 Reading List (Fall 1959) (Box 14)
  - Doctoral Committees (1950-1960) (Box 14)
  - Workload Records (1950-1960) (Box 14)
  - ECO 460 Economic Development for Non-Economic Majors (Fall 1974), (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - ECO 441 Lectures, 1970and 1975, (3 folders) (Box 14)
- General Correspondence Series, 1966and 1974 (Box 14)
  This series is presently sparse, containing only a couple of letters that were found loose among the folders.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 14)
- Accession 2002-0207 (Box 14)